<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-15"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN">
<article>
    <articleinfo>
	<title>CryptoFS</title>
	<author>
	    <firstname>Christoph</firstname>
	    <surname>Hohmann</surname>
	    <honorific>B.Sc</honorific>
	    <affiliation>
		<address><email>reboot@gmx.ch</email></address>
    	    </affiliation>
	</author>
	<copyright>
    	    <year>2003-2006</year>
    	    <holder>Christoph Hohmann</holder>
	</copyright>
    </articleinfo>
    <sect1>
    	<title>What's CryptoFS</title>
	<para>
	    CryptoFS is a encrypted filesystem for Filesystem in Userspace
	    (FUSE) and the Linux Userland FileSystem (LUFS).  Visit <ulink
	    url="http://fuse.sourceforge.net/">http://fuse.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
	    for more information on FUSE or <ulink
	    url="http://lufs.sourceforge.net/lufs/">http://lufs.sourceforge.net/lufs/</ulink>
	    for more information on LUFS.
	</para>
        <para>
	    CryptoFS will use a normal directory to store files encrypted.
	    The mountpoint will contain the decrypted files. Every file
	    stored in this mountpoint will be written encrypted (data
	    and filename) to the directory that was mounted. If you
	    unmount the directory the encrypted data can only be access
	    by mounting the directory with the correct key again. Like
	    other FUSE/LUFS filesystems it does not need root access
	    or any complicated setup like creating a filesystem on a
	    encrypted disk using the loop device.
        </para>
	<para>
	    CryptoFS can be build for FUSE and LUFS. When you build for
	    FUSE you get a program to mount the filesystem. For LUFS a
	    shared library will be built that can be used by LUFS's lufsd.
	    Both methods can use the same encrypted directory.
	</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
	<title>Why CryptoFS?</title>
	<para>
	    I first used the evfs kernel patch that does nearly the same thing
	    as CryptoFS. But it seems that it has been abandoned. The last patch
	    was available for kernel 2.4.20 and has not been updated for newer
	    kernels since then. When I found LUFS I thought I could be a good
	    base for a crypto filesystem that works like evfs and allows a user
	    to mount any directory as an encrypted storage without having root
	    access and creating a crypto filesystem using the loop device. So
	    when I found no other program that offers this posibilities I started
	    to write my own filesystem for LUFS. Unfortunately LUFS seems to be
	    dead too, so CryptoFS can now be build for FUSE too which has already
	    made it into the official Linux kernel package.
	</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
	<title>Requirements</title>
	<para>
	    You either need FUSE or LUFS to use CryptoFS.
	    For FUSE you need the FUSE tools, library and
	    kernel module.  You also need the FUSE development
	    files to build the FUSE filesystem. See <ulink
	    url="http://fuse.sourceforge.net/">http://fuse.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
	    for more information and downloads. If you don't want to build
	    CryptoFS for FUSE you can use the --disable-fuse configure
	    switch. Otherwise it will be build when the development files
	    are found on the system. For LUFS you only have to install
	    the LUFS tools and load the LUFS kernel module. See <ulink
	    url="http://lufs.sourceforge.net/lufs/">http://lufs.sourceforge.net/lufs/</ulink>
	    on how to do this and downloads for LUFS. If you want
	    to disable building CryptoFS for LUFS you can use the
	    --disable-lufs configure switch.  As the LUFS module has no
	    requirements it will be build by default.	 Installing and
	    setting up LUFS and FUSE will not be covered by this document.
	</para>
	<para>
	    CryptoFS uses Libgcrypt from <ulink
	    url="ftp://ftp.gnupg.org/gcrypt/alpha/libgcrypt/">ftp://ftp.gnupg.org/gcrypt/alpha/libgcrypt/</ulink>
	    (version >= 1.1.44) and GLib from <ulink
	    url="http://www.gtk.org">http://www.gtk.org</ulink>
	    (version >= 2.6). You must have installed these packages
	    correctly before running CryptoFS's "configure" script.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Optionally CryptoFS can use the <ulink
	    url="ftp://ftp.gnupg.org/gcrypt/pinentry/">PIN Entry</ulink>
	    utility by <ulink url="http://www.gnupg.org/">GnuPG</ulink>
	    to ask the user for the filesystem's password. If the pinentry
	    program is found on the system CryptoFS will be automatically
	    built with PIN Entry support. Otherwise it will fall back
	    to the old console input method.
	</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
	<title>Usage</title>
        <para>
	    First you have to set up the source directory by copying
	    the file cryptofs.conf to &lt;source&gt;/.cryptofs. Where
	    &lt;source&gt; is the directory where you want to store
	    the encryted files. You can adjust the values in the file,
	    but the default should work fine.
	</para>
	<para>
	    For FUSE you have to run cryptofs that should be in an executeable
	    path after "make install". The required options are
	    <programlisting><![CDATA[     cryptofs --root=<source> <dest> ]]></programlisting>
	    &lt;dest&gt; is the directory where the filesystem containing
	    the decrypted files will be mounted.
	</para>
	<para>		    
    	    For LUFS put the shared library into a directory where the system linker can find
	    it (this will usually be done by "make install") or add the directory
	    to the search path by setting the LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment varibale.
	</para>
	<para>
	    After that you can mount the source directory with
	    <programlisting><![CDATA[     lufsmount cryptofs://<source> <dest> ]]></programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	    You will be asked for the password you want to use for this filesystem. It
	    will be used to generate the cipher key.
	</para>
	<para>
	    After that you should be able to use the &lt;dest&gt; directory like any other
	    directory, but all data will be read and written to the &lt;source&gt; directory
	    in an encrypted form.
	</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
	<title>How does it work?</title>
	<sect2>
	    <title>The .cryptofs config file</title>
	    <para>
		The CryptoFS config file in each encryted directory contains 4 options.
		These are
		<variablelist>
		    <varlistentry>
			<term>cipher</term>
			<listitem>
			    <para>
				The cipher algorithm used to encrypt files and filenames.
				This has to be a cipher name known by libgcrypt.
			    </para>
			</listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		    <varlistentry>
			<term>md</term>
			<listitem>
			    <para>
				The message digest algorithm used to generate the cipher
				key. This has to be a message digest name known by
				libgcrypt.
			    </para>
			</listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		    <varlistentry>
			<term>blocksize</term>
			<listitem>
			    <para>
				An encrypted file can not be randomly accessed like a normal
				file and CryptoFS always reads and writes blocks of this size.
			    </para>
			</listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		    <varlistentry>
			<term>salts</term>
			<listitem>
			    <para>
				This is the number of subkeys CryptoFS will generate to
				encrypt blocks.
			    </para>
			</listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<emphasis>NOTE:</emphasis> Before 0.4.0 CryptoFS used a different config file format.
		The LUFS module can still read this format. The FUSE program only supports
		the new format. If you want to switch from LUFS to FUSE you have to
	        replace .cryptofs with a file in the new format.
	    </para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	    <title>Encryption</title>
	    <para>
		When a filesystem is mounted CryptoFS first generates a key for the
		requested cipher algorithm (cipher option) using the message
		digest function (md option). Every algorithm has a specific key size
		and every message digest function has a specific length of the
		generated message digest. If the message digest size is smaller then
		the keysize the message digest will be repeated until the key size
		is reached.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		After they primary key has been generated n (= salts option= subkeys
		(initialization vectors) will be generated by encrypting 0 bytes with
		a 0 initialization vector. These will later be used to encrypt blocks
		with different subkeys to make sure the cipher text will first repeat
		after (salts * blocksize) bytes (If the same data is encrypted).
	    </para>
	    <para>
		When files or links are created or renamed the name will be encoded
		with the selected cipher, the primary key and the first subkey.
		The result will then be encoded using a modified Base64 algorithm
		because the encrypted filename could contain characters that are not
		allowed by the target filesystem. (The original Base64 algorithm
		uses '/' for encoding. This is the directory delimiter so it was
		replaced by '_')
	    </para>
	    <para>
		When files are written the data will be encrypted. CryptoFS always
		has to write full blocks. So if only a part of a block should be
		written the original block will first be read, decrypted, the part
		replaced and then the result then written encrypted back to disk.
		To keep this performant that block size must not be too large.
		But to make sure the cipher text does not repeat to early, CryptoFS
		uses salts to encrypt blocks. Every block will be encoded with
		the (blocknumber module salts)th salt. (NOTE: Linux always reads
		or writes "pages" of size 4096 bytes, these writes will be
		forwarded by lufsd to CryptoFS. So if you use a blocksize of
		4096 bytes reading the old block before writing can be omitted
		and writing should be faster)
	    </para>
	</sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
	<title>Download</title>
	<para>{download}</para>
    </sect1>
</article>
